Mss.B.P274 Mss.B.P274
American Philosophical Society
Robert M. (Robert Maskell) Patterson papers, 1775-1853
Mss.B.P274
American Philosophical Society
0.5 Linear feet
Robert Maskell Patterson (1787-1854, APS 1809) was a professor of chemistry and natural philosophy at the University of Pennsylvania (1812-1828) and professor of natural philosophy at the University of Virginia (1828-1835). He was director of the U.S. Mint from 1835 to 1851. His father, Robert Patterson, was a revolutionary soldier, professor of mathematics at the University of Pennsylvania (1779-1814), and director of the U.S. Mint (1805-1824).
Ca. 450 items.
Patterson,, Robert M., (Robert Maskell), 1787-1854
Box 1
Volume 1-5
Scope and Contents note
This collection includes letters to and from A. D. Bache, John Gummere, Ferdinand R. Hassler, Samuel M. Leiper, Robert C. Reid, John Sergeant, John Vaughan, and others. Fifteen letters are to President Franklin Pierce from various persons recommending Robert Maskell Patterson's son for the directorship of the Mint, 1853. There is a large number of miscellaneous notes and papers on a great variety of topics, including astronomy, algebra, annuities, coal, canals, electricity, magnetism, optics, sound, the deaths of Adams and Jefferson, music, and natural philosophy.
Naval History Note
The Patterson Papers contain at least two letters with references to Oliver Hazard Perry:
Perry, Oliver Hazard, 1785-1819.
Reid, Robert. Letter to Robert Patterson. 1813 June 28. News of the war, refers to Oliver Hazard Perry. 3 pages.
Reid, Robert. Letter to Robert Patterson. 1813 October 25. Concerning the war, describes Harrison and Oliver Hazard Perry, and tells of the death of Tecumseh. 3 pages.
Early American History Note
The Robert Patterson Collection contains a range of documents that touch on many different topics, although most have to do with science and engineering. The earliest documents relate to the Leiper Canal, including Rittenhouse’s appraisal of it, and official documents relating to its creation. The largest portion of the documents is scientific correspondence to Robert Patterson, a member of the American Philosophical Society. Much of this correspondence is done under the cover of official APS business. Of particular note are a series of letters relating to nautical calculations that include complex equations used to determine longitude and latitude for nautical almanacs. There are also various lecture notes on natural philosophy, death, mathematics, engineering, and other subjects.
In addition to the notes, there is a class roster from the Universities of Pennsylvania and Virginia and copies of exams. There is also meteorological data for 1775 and 1776.
There is a series of letters from Robert Reid writing to Patterson from Erie, Pennsylvania during the War of 1812. He discusses various battles on the lakes and makes mention of Tecumseh.
Also of note is an elaborate mathematical formula Patterson constructed to determine the odds that Jefferson and Adams would die on the same day, which he put at 1.7 billion to one. There are a series of letters from prominent Philadelphians writing to President Franklin Pierce advocating Robert Patterson’s appointment as Director of the Philadelphia Mint.
Biographical/Historical note
Robert Maskell Patterson (1787-1854, APS 1809) was a professor of chemistry and natural philosophy at the University of Pennsylvania (1812-1828) and professor of natural philosophy at the University of Virginia (1828-1835). He was director of the U.S. Mint from 1835 to 1851. His father, Robert Patterson, was a revolutionary soldier, professor of mathematics at the University of Pennsylvania (1779-1814), and director of the U.S. Mint (1805-1824).
Robert Maskell Patterson was born in 1787 into a prominent Philadelphia family. His father was Robert Patterson (1743-1824, APS 1783), at the time professor of mathematics at the University of Pennsylvania (1779-1814) and subsequently director of the United States Mint (1805 to 1824). He served as president of the American Philosophical Society from 1819 until his death. Robert Maskell Patterson’s mother was Amy Hunter Ewing.
Patterson was educated at the University of Pennsylvania’s preparatory school, received his B.A. in 1804, and then went on to study medicine at the University under Benjamin Smith Barton (1766-1815, APS 1759). He earned his M.D. in 1808. As his friend John Kintzing Kane (1795-1858, APS 1825) noted in his 1854 obituary, “Dr. Patterson was an inmate of the University almost from his cradle.”
After graduation Patterson went to Paris to pursue his studies at the Jardins des Plantes. He worked with a number of prominent scientists, including Louis Nicolas Vauquelin (1763-1829), Adrien-Marie Legendre (1752-1833), and Siméon Denis Poisson (1781-1840), who encouraged him to study natural history, chemistry, and mathematics. In 1811 he went to England to complete his training in chemistry with Humphry Davy (1778-1829, APS 1810) at London.
Shortly after his return to Philadelphia in 1812, Patterson was appointed professor of natural philosophy in the medical department of the University of Pennsylvania. He subsequently also became professor of natural history, chemistry and mathematics in the faculty of arts. In 1814 he assumed the post of Vice Provost. That same year he married Helen Hamilton Leiper (1792-1871), daughter of the merchant and politician Thomas Leiper (1745-1825). The couple had six children.
Around this time Patterson was involved in identifying and acquiring suitable books and instruments for Ferdinand R. Hassler’s (1770–1843, APS 1807) planned coastal survey. The elder Patterson belonged to a group of APS members that had been instrumental in the establishment of a Coast Survey in 1807. Robert Patterson had selected Hassler as its director that year, and, after many delays due to financial problems and difficulties in obtaining suitable instruments, Hassler was finally scheduled to conduct the first survey in 1816-1817. Hassler turned to the APS for assistance, and both father and son probably contributed to a list of useful literature and apparatus. In 1826 Patterson was selected by the Pennsylvania governor to determine the best source of water for the planned state canal.
Patterson remained at the University of Pennsylvania until 1828, when he accepted the chair in natural philosophy at the University of Virginia. He routinely used a large collection of apparatus during his lectures and demonstrations. He evidently was an effective teacher; his colleague and friend Robley Dunglison (1798-1869, APS 1832) recalled that “As a lecturer of science, Dr. Patterson was one of the most successful I have ever heard.” His student John Fries Frazer (1812–1872, APS 1842) noted that from Patterson “he received the best and most effective lessons in the art of teaching.” However, his appointment in 1835 as director of the United States Mint took him out of the classroom and back to Philadelphia. There he drew up a code of mint laws which included changes in the composition of the alloys in the coins. He remained at the Mint until around 1851 when poor health compelled him to curtail his activities. Kane recalled that Patterson passed “unscathed through the purgatory of several political conflicts, and their alternating denunciations of triumph.”
At the age of twenty-two, Patterson was elected to the American Philosophical Society, the youngest man admitted during the first century of the Society’s existence. In 1813 he was elected one of the secretaries, and in 1825 he was chosen as a vice president. From 1849 until his death he served as the Society’s president. He also belonged to the Academy of Natural Science, the Franklin Institute, which he helped found, the Musical Fund Society, and the Institution for the Blind. He was a trustee of Old Scots Presbyterian Church and president of the Pennsylvania Life Annuity Company. Patterson also belonged to the “Five Club,” a social club that also included Kane, Dunglison, George W. Bethune, and Alexander Dallas Bache (1806-1867, APS 1829), and that met regularly for conversation. Their meetings, according to Judge Kane, were “quiet, joyous, and instructive.”
Patterson died in Philadelphia in 1854.
Adams, John, 1735-1826; Bache, A.D., (Alexander Dallas), 1806-1867; Freeman, Thomas,d. 1821.; Garnett, John, 1748 or 51-1820; Girard College.; Gummere, John, 1784-1845; Hassler, F. R, (Ferdinand Rudolph), 1770-1843; Jefferson, Thomas, 1743-1826; Leiper, Samuel M.; Leiper, Thomas, 1745-1825; Patterson, Robert, 1743-1824; Pemberton, Phineas; Pierce, Franklin, 1804-1869; Reid, Robert C.; Sergeant, John, 1779-1852; U.S. Coast and Geodetic Survey.; United States Mint.; University of Pennsylvania.; University of Virginia.; Vaughan, John, 1756-1841; Algebra.; Americans Abroad; Annuities.; Astronomy.; Canals.; Clocks and watches.; Coal.; Early National Politics; Education; Educational Material; Electricity.; General Correspondence; Institutional Records; Lectures.; Magnetism.; Mathematics.; Meteorology -- Observations.; Military History; Native America; Navigation (Astronautics); Notebooks; Optics.; Physics.; Political Correspondence; Quarries and quarrying -- Pennsylvania.; Science and Technology; Sound.; Time clocks.; Travel Narratives and Journals; War of 1812
- Series One: Papers
  - Papers, 1804-1836; Patterson, Robert M. (Robert Maskell), 1787-1854
    Scope and Contents note
    D. 29 items, 5 volumes,(board), and 2 printed items. Various sizes. Table of contents available.
  - Meteorological observations, Jan. 1, July 6, 1775-1777; 8x6-1/2; Pemberton, Israel, 1715-1779
    Philadelphia, A.D. 58p. (see Patterson Papers.) Presented to the APS by J. Pemberton. Cf. Minutes, pp.192, 264, 268, 274, 276, and 278.
  - Certification of the value of Leiper's canal, Sept.15, 1791; 7-1/2x7; Rittenhouse, David, 1732-1796
    [ca.] A.D.S.: Davd Rittenhouse and Jno.Ewing. 1p. (see Patterson papers.) Tipped in, under Rittenhouse's endorsement: see J. Brindley. Calculations...; Aug. 18, 1791.
  - Calculations of the water level for Leiper's and Wall's proposed canal, Aug. 18, 1791; 9x7-1/2; Brindley, James
    Philadelphia, D.S. 8p.and end.by D.Rittenhouse, and end. (see Patterson papers.) Tipped in under Rittenhouse's endorsement is: Rittenhouse. Certificate...; [ca.Sept.15,1791].
  - Draft of proposed canal, 1791; 15x38-1/2; Leiper, Thomas, 1745-1825
    [ca.?]. D. 1p.and end. (see Patterson papers.)
  - Petition to the Pennsylvania Senate for Leiper to build his canal, [ca. 1791]; Philadelphia. City commissioners
  - Petition to the Pennsylvania House of representatives for permission for Leiper to build his canal, [ca. 1791]; 15x9-1/2; Philadelphia. City commissioners
    D.S.: William Penrose and 22 others. 1p. (see Patterson papers)
  - Petition to the House of representatives for permission to build a canal, 1791; 16x10; Leiper, Thomas, 1745-1825
    [ca.]. D.S. 3p (see Patterson papers
  - Minutes, Jan. 25, 1792; 15x9; Pennsylvania. General Assembly. House of Representatives.
    D. 12p.with correction in hand of R. Patterson (?). Copy. (see Patterson Papers.) Fisher's argument for permission for Leiper to erect his dam for his canal.
  - Certificate of the value of Leiper's stone, Jan. 27, 1792; 4-1/2x8; Taylor, Benjamin
    Philadelphia, D.S.: Benjamin Taylor, George Justice, and Frederick Vogel. 1p.and end. (see Patterson papers.)
  - Minutes, Jan. 27, [1792?]; 12-1/2x8; Pennsylvania. General Assembly. House of Representatives
    D. 8p. Copy. (see Patterson Papers.) Debate on Leiper's petition for permission to build a canal.
  - Certificate concerning Leiper's proposed canal, [ca. 1792]; Francis, Tench, 1730-1800
  - An act to authorize Thomas Leiper to establish a canal on Crum Creek, 1792; 16x10; Pennsylvania. General Assembly
    [ca.] D. 3p. (see Patterson papers)
  - Hints towards a primer for my little boy [Robert M. Patterson], 1793; 6-1/2x4; Patterson, Robert, 1743-1824
    [ca.]. A.D. 23p. (see Patterson Papers.) In same volume is: Mary P. Patterson. Note to go with "Hints..."; July 8,1937; and E.W. Nevins: Codicil...; May 16,1863.
  - Notebook, 1800; 7-1/2x6; Patterson, Robert M. (Robert Maskell), 1787-1854
    [ca.] A.D. 19p.of 102p. (see Patterson Papers.) Medicine, natural history, etc. Included in this is: [R.M.Patterson] Lecture notes...; [ca.1804?].
  - Letter to Robert Patterson, Philadelphia, Jan. 27, 1801; 10x8; Miller, Samuel, 1769-1850
    New York, A.L.S. 3p. and add.,end. (see Patterson papers.) Concerning his forthcoming publication on the U.S.in the 18th Century and asks for help on mathematics, astronomy, Rittenhouse, orrery, Godfrey's quadrant, etc.
  - Letter to Robert Patterson, Philadelphia, June 27, 1801; 9x7; Garnett, John, 1748 or 51-1820
    New Brunswick, A.L.S. 3p.and add. (see Patterson Papers.) Suggests simplier method of finding longitude as an aid to navigation. Refers to APS.
  - Letter to [Robert Patterson], Jan. 14, 1802; 9x7-1/2; Garnett, John, 1748 or 51-1820
    New Brunswick, A.L.S. 2p.and end.: "read [to the APS] 15th Jany." (see Patterson Papers.) Concerning logarithms.
  - Letter to Robert Patterson, Philadelphia, Jan. 14, 1804; 9x7; Garnett, John, 1748 or 51-1820
    New Brunswick, A.L.S. 1p.and add. (see Patterson Papers.) Concerning problems with lunar tables.
  - Certificate as to the value of Leiper's quarry and need for his canal, Feb. 20, 1804; 10x8; Chesapeake and Delaware Canal Company
    Philadelphia, D.S.: W[illia]m Tilghman and Jos. Gilpin. 1p.and end. (see Patterson papers.)
  - Statement concerning the quality of stone for building, referring to Leiper and his mill at Crum-Creek, Feb. 20, 1804; 8x8-1/4; Fraquair, James
    Philadelphia, D.S. 1p.and end. (see Patterson papers.)
  - Certificate of the value of Leiper's quarries, Feb. 20, 1804; 6x8; Taylor, Charles
    Philadelphia, A.D.S. 1p. (see Patterson Papers.) Given to help Leiper get permission to build a canal.
  - Letter to John Garnett, New Brunswick, July 28, 1804; 10x8; Patterson, Robert, 1743-1824
    Philadelphia, A.L.S. 3p.and add. (see Patterson Papers.) Suggestions to simplify Garnett's aids for navigation.
  - Letter to R[obert] Patterson, Philadelphia, Sept. 20, 1804; 9-1/2x7-1/2; Garnett, John, 1748 or 51-1820
    New Brunswick, A.L.S. 3p.and add. (see Patterson Papers.) Concerning lunar observations and logarithms for seamen.
  - Letter to Robert Patterson, Philadelphia, Oct. 12, 1804; 9x7-1/2; Garnett, John, 1748 or 51-1820
    New Brunswick, A.L.S. 3p.and add. (see Patterson Papers.) Lunar observations. Concerning astronomical observations and longitude. Refers to J.Vaughan.
  - Letter to Robert Patterson, Philadelphia, Dec. 26, 1804; 9x7-1/2; Garnett, John, 1748 or 51-1820
    New Brunswick, A.L.S. 4p.,add. (see Patterson Papers.) Concerning the finding of latitude. Donates volume to the APS.
  - Certificate of the quality of stone from Leiper's quarries, 1804; 9x7-1/2; O'Neale, William
    [ca.]. D.S. 2p.,end. (see Patterson Papers.) Given to help Lieper get permission to build his canal.
  - Certificate of the value of the stone from Leiper's quarries, 1804; 5-1/2x8; Vickers, Thomas
    [ca.]. D.S. 1p.and end. (see Patterson Papers.) Given to help Lieper get permission to build a canal.
  - Observations on the Crum Creek canal, to the Chairman of the House of representatives, 1804?; 9x7-1/2; Leiper, Thomas, 1745-1825
    [ca.]. D. 15p.and end. (see Patterson Papers.) Concerning the need of the canal. Refers to Rittenhouse.
  - Tables for finding latitude and longitude in navigation, [1804?]; 9x15; Garnett, John, 1748 or 51-1820
    ca. A.D. 2p. Sent to Robert Patterson. (see Patterson Papers.)
  - Lecture notes on natural philosophy from Dr. Moyes's lectures, 1804?; 7-1/2x6; Patterson, Robert M. (Robert Maskell), 1787-1854
    [ca.?] A.D. 74p.of 102p. (see Patterson Papers.) Refers to Franklin. See volume: [R.M. Patterson] Notebook; [ca.1800], pp.20-94. Not found April, 2011.
  - Letter to Robert Patterson, Philadelphia, Aug. 30, 1805; 9x7-1/2; Garnett, John, 1748 or 51-1820
    New Brunswick, A.L.S. 3p.and add. (see Patterson Papers.) Logarithms in astronomy. Friendly letter.
  - Etymological notes, 1805-1806; 7-1/2x6-1/2; Patterson, Robert M. (Robert Maskell), 1787-1854
    A.D. 5p. (see Patterson Papers.)
  - Label: Garnett's letters and others miscellany including some to the P[hilosophical] Society..., 1805; 7-1/2x6; Patterson, Robert M. (Robert Maskell), 1787-1854
    A.D.S. 2p. (see Patterson Papers.)
  - Letter to Rob[er]t Patterson, Philadelphia, Jan. 13, 1806; 10x8; Freeman, Thomas, d. 1821
    Washington, Mississippi Territory, A.L.S. 2p.and add. (see Patterson Papers.) Friendly letter. Refers to Barton and Dunbar.
  - Letter to R[obert] Patterson, May 19, 1806; 18x11; Garnett, John, 1748 or 51-1820
    New Brunswick, A.L.S. 4p. (see Patterson Papers.) Concerning problems in astronomy. Refers to Hassler.
  - Letter to Robert Patterson, Philadelphia, Aug. 10, 1806; 9-1/2x7-1/2; Garnett, John, 1748 or 51-1820
    New Brunswick, A.L.S. 3p.and add. (see Patterson Papers.) Concerning the locating of latitude.
  - Letter to Robert Patterson, Philadelphia, Dec. 20, 1806; 9x7-1/2; Garnett, John, 1748 or 51-1820
    New Brunswick, A.L.S. 2p.and add. (see Patterson Papers.) Concerning longitude. Forwards publications to the APS. Refers to Hassler.
  - Letter to Robert Patterson, Philadelphia, Jan. 18, 1807; 9x7; Garnett, John, 1748 or 51-1820
    New Brunswick, A.L.S. 3p.and add. (see Patterson Papers.) Concerning his publication as an aid to navigation. Refers to Jonathan Williams and Hassler.
  - Letter to Robert Patterson, Philadelphia, Jan. 25, 1807; 9-1/2x7-1/2; Garnett, John, 1748 or 51-1820
    New Brunswick, A.L.S. 4p.,add. (see Patterson Papers.) Concerning his printing an aid for navigation.
  - Letter to Robert Patterson, Philadelphia, Jan. 31, [1807?]; 9x7-1/2; Garnett, John, 1748 or 51-1820
    A.L.S. 3p.and add. (see Patterson Papers.) Concerning his publication on navigation.
  - Letter to Robert Patterson, Philadelphia, Feb. 3, 1807; 9x7-1/2; Garnett, John, 1748 or 51-1820
    Elizabethtown, A.L.S. 2p.and add. (see Patterson Papers.) Concerning the route in sailing the great circle route.
  - Letter to John Dorsey, March 20, 1807; 10x8; Patterson, Robert, 1743-1824
    Philadelphia, L.S. 4p.,end. (see Patterson Papers.) Concerning weights and measures. Refers to Jefferson and to the APS.
  - Letter to Robert Patterson, Philadelphia, March 29, 1807; 14x8-1/2; Garnett, John, 1748 or 51-1820
    New Brunswick, A.L.S. 1p.and add. (see Patterson Papers.) Concerning charts for his aid to navigation. Refers to Jonathan Williams and Hassler.
  - Letter to [Robert Patterson], May 6, 1807; 9x7-1/2; Garnett, John, 1748 or 51-1820
    New Brunswick, A.L.S. 4p. (see Patterson Papers.) Concerning longitude and latitude. Refers to Hassler and Jonathan Williams.
  - Letter to Robert Patterson, Philadelphia, May 7, 1807; 9x7-1/2; Garnett, John, 1748 or 51-1820
    New Brunswick, A.L.S. 3p.and add. (see Patterson Papers.) Refers to the APS publications. Concerning latitude and longitude. Refers to Hassler.
  - Letter to Robert Patterson, Philadelphia, June 29, 1807; 9x7-1/2; Garnett, John, 1748 or 51-1820
    New Brunswick, A.L.S. 1p.and add.,end. (see Patterson Papers.) Navigation aids. Requests a favor.
  - Letter to Robert Patterson, Philadelphia, July 8, 1807; 9x7-1/2; Garnett, John, 1748 or 51-1820
    New Brunswick, A.L.S. 1p.and add. (see Patterson Papers.) Forwards publication to the APS. Refers to Hassler.
  - Letter to Robert Patterson, Philadelphia, Aug. 8, 1807; 9x7-1/2; Garnett, John, 1748 or 51-1820
    New Brunswick, A.L.S. 2p.and add. (see Patterson Papers.) Concerning latitude for navigation. Refers to the Magellanic premium from the society.
  - Letter to [Robert Patterson], Aug. 14, 1807; 9x7; Garnett, John, 1748 or 51-1820
    New Brunswick, A.L.S. 4p. (see Patterson Papers.) Concerning the finding of longitude.
  - Letter to Robert Patterson, Philadelphia, Aug. 20, 1807; 8x6-1/2; Garnett, John, 1748 or 51-1820
    New Brunswick, A.L.S. 2p.and add. (see Patterson Papers.) Concerning his publication which will aid in navigation.
  - Letter to Robert Patterson, Philadelphia, Aug. 28, 1807; 9x7-1/2; Garnett, John, 1748 or 51-1820
    New Brunswick, A.L.S. 3p.and add. (see Patterson Papers.) Concerning nautical charts for his aid for navigation.
  - Receipt to Robert Scott for copper plates [purchased by Robert Patterson for John Garnett?], Sept. 6, 1807; 3x8; Oat, Jesse
    Philadelphia, D.S.: Charlotte Oat for Jesse Oat. 1p. (see Patterson Papers.)
  - Brief analysis and report of committee on Garnett's entry for the Extra Magellanic premium, Sept. 17, 1807; 9-1/2x8 and 12-1/2x8; American Philosophical Society
    D.S.: Peter S. DuPonceau and J[oh]n Vaughan. 2p.and end. (see Patterson Papers.) See Minutes, p.399.
  - Letter to Robert Patterson, Philadelphia, Oct. 16, 1807; 9x7; Garnett, John, 1748 or 51-1820
    L. 3p.and add. (see Patterson Papers.) Concerning his aid for navigation and astronomical observations. Refers to John Vaughan.
  - Letter to Robert Patterson, Philadelphia, Oct. 19, 1807; 9x7-1/2; Garnett, John, 1748 or 51-1820
    New Brunswick, A.L.S. 2p.and add. (see Patterson Papers.) Thanks to the American philosophical society for the Magellanic premium. Concerning his aid for navigation.
  - Description of a new nautical chart, [1807]; 16-1/2x10; Garnett, John, 1748 or 51-1820
    D. 8p.,with add.in Robert Patterson's hand, and end. Directed to [the American philosophical society]. (see Patterson Papers.) Winner of the Extra Magellanic premium. Printed: Trans.,v.6, art.49, 1809.
  - Letter to Robert M[askell] Patterson, Paris, Aug. 17, 1809; 9-1/2x8; Reid, Robert C.
    Philadelphia, A.L.S. 3p.and add.,end. (see Patterson Papers.) Friendly letter.
  - Letter to Thomas Jefferson, Dec. 8, 1809; 16-1/2x10-1/2; Lambert, William
    Washington, A.L.S. 8p.,end.: "read [to the APS] Jan. 19, 1810." (see Patterson papers.) How to compute the moon's longitude and how to compute its velocity. See Minutes, p.420.
  - Problems in astronomical observations, [1809]; 10x8; Patterson, Robert M. (Robert Maskell), 1787-1854
    A.D.S. 1vol.consisting of 55p. (see Patterson Papers, No. 2.)
  - Principles of vegetables, according to Thénard, Jan. 10, 1810; 9x7; Patterson, Robert M. (Robert Maskell), 1787-1854
    A.D. 4p. (see Patterson Papers.)
  - Letter to Robert Patterson, Philadelphia, March 10, 1810; 9-1/2x8; Garnett, John, 1748 or 51-1820
    New Brunswick, A.L.S. 3p.and add. (see Patterson Papers.) Concerning Lambert's lunar tables. Refers to J.Vaughan.
  - Letter to R[obert] M. Patterson, Paris, May 24, 1810; 10x8; Reid, Robert C.
    Philadelphia, A.L.S. 3p.and add.to D.B.Warden, end. (see Patterson Papers.) Friendly letter.
  - Letter to Robert C. Reid, Nov. 17, 1810; 9-1/2x7; Patterson, Robert M. (Robert Maskell), 1787-1854
    Paris, A.L.S. 2p.and add.,end. (see Patterson Papers.) Friendly letter.
  - Letter to Robert Patterson, Philadelphia, Dec. 26, 1810; 9-1/2x8; Freeman, Thomas, d. 1821
    Washington, Mississippi Territory, A.L.S. 4p.,add.,end. (see Patterson Papers.) Asks favor. Friendly letter. Death of Dunbar.
  - Lecture notes on dyeing, from Thénard, 1810?; 9x7; Patterson, Robert M. (Robert Maskell), 1787-1854
    [ca.] A.D. 3p. (see Patterson Papers)
  - Letter to Robert M[askell] Patterson, Paris, Jan. 7, 1811; 10x8; Reid, Robert C.
    Philadelphia, A.L.S. 3p.and add.,end. (see Patterson Papers.) Friendly letter. Refers to Jefferson and Barton.
  - Letter to Rob[er]t Patterson, Philadelphia, July 15, 1811; 10x8; Freeman, Thomas, d. 1821
    Washington, Mississippi Territory, A.L.S. 2p.and add. (see Patterson Papers.) Friendly letter.
  - Letter to Robert Patterson, Philadelphia, Aug. 19, 1811; 10x8; Freeman, Thomas, d. 1821